Hello, English learners
and welcome to another
great lesson with us
here at English pod.
My name is Marco
and I'm Erica and today
we're bringing you a great
upper intermediate lesson.
That's right.
We're going to talk
about a topic that's been
in the news recently and
this topic is the bird flu.
That's right.
So can you tell us what
the bird flu really is?
Basically the story is
a lot of chickens and
birds keep getting
this disease and they've
managed to pass this disease to humans and
the fear is that humans will start to pass
this disease to each
other in a huge, huge
number of people in the
world could get really sick.
Okay.
So it sounds scary.
Well, it may be a little bit scary but
we do have some interesting language.
We've got language
to talk about a disease
and language that you might
use in a planning meeting at work.
Alright.
So let's start by looking at our
vocabulary preview for this dialogue.
vocabulary preview.
Okay.
The first word on our
vocabulary preview today is
contingency plan, contingency plan,
contingency plan, contingency plan.
So a contingency plan is a plan that
you make to prepare for an emergency.
So like a backup plan.
Exactly.
Okay.
Yeah.
Tingency plan.
And our last word for the vocabulary preview
today is pandemic, pandemic, pandemic.
So a pandemic is something scary.
Well, yes.
It's an event where a
disease affects a lot of
people, like we're
talking millions of people.
Okay.
And it spreads very quickly
and it goes international.
Okay.
So a disease that spreads
very fast and goes everywhere.
Exactly.
Okay.
Pandemic.
So we're ready to listen to our dialogue.
We are going to be
at a business meeting
where people are talking
about a contingency plan.
Well, right.
Let's move to our next order of business.
As many of you are aware,
in recent weeks, there
has been a lot of media coverage
surrounding this bird flu issue.
And it's come to my
attention that our company
lacks any sort of bird
flu contingency plan.
Basically, we need to
come up with a clear plan.
We need to outline
specific actions that our
company can take to maintain critical
business functions in case a pandemic strikes.
So what I'd like to do is first point
someone to look after drafting our plan.
Ralph, I'd like you to
head up this project.
Sure.
No problem.
What issues do you want me to consider?
Well, let's see.
There are a few points we
need to be thinking about.
First, I'll need you to
analyze our numbers
and figure out what kind of
financial impact an outbreak I have.
You will also need to
think about how we can
avoid any of our
employees getting infected.
Think of ways to reduce
employee customer
contact, perhaps some IT solutions that
will allow our people to work from home.
I guess you'll need me to focus
employee absences as well, right?
And I'll think about the impact
this will have on our clients.
Hey, what about vaccines?
Should be the thinking about
getting vaccines for employees.
Exactly right.
So I'll leave this to you and well,
we'll review the draft plan in two weeks.
Okay.
So anyone want to order some KFC for lunch?
All right, what an
ironic meeting they are
talking about the bird flu and
they are going to have chicken.
Yes.
It's sneezing all over.
Yeah, I guess now we could take a look
at our language takeaway for this dialogue.
Language takeaway.
We heard a lot of really useful language in
this dialogue and right now we're going to
look at four different
words from the dialogue.
The first one is critical,
critical, critical, critical.
We've got some examples of this word that
will help us to understand the meaning.
So let's listen.
Number one, it's absolutely
critical that we increase our sales.
If not, the company will go bankrupt.
Example two.
We have a critical shortage of food.
If we don't get help, people will die.
Example three.
This is a critical step in the process.
You can't make a mistake here.
So when something's critical, it's
basically really important, really urgent.
Right.
Okay, great word, critical.
The next word we have is outbreak.
outbreak.
So when outbreak is a
sudden start of a disease, right?
Can I say, oh, I got an outbreak of flu.
Can outbreak describe one person?
No, an outbreak means that
it's infecting a lot of people.
Okay.
Not only one person.
So that we could say there was an
outbreak of the flu at the office, right?
Which there was.
Yeah.
A lot of people got sick here with the flu.
Okay.
Why don't you tell us about our third word?
Our third word is forecast.
Forecast.
So to forecast basically means to predict.
Exactly.
For example, you talk
about the weather forecast.
Yep.
Great.
And the last word for our language
takeaway is vaccines vaccines vaccines.
So vaccines are something we
all had when we were children.
That's true.
They are injections that you get to
prevent you from getting sick later.
Right.
So an injection of
medicine from your doctor
so that you don't get
a disease in the future.
Right.
When we are small, we get polio vaccine.
Yeah.
A lot of common diseases.
Yes.
Okay.
So that's all for
language take away some
great language related
to health and disease.
But we also heard some great
business related words in this dialogue.
That's true.
There's a lot of words that you
can use in a planning meeting.
So let's look at those
now in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
In today's fluency builder, we're
going to look at four useful phrases.
Now this first phrase you can use when you
want to change the subject at a meeting.
Let's listen to what
they said in the dialogue.
Let's move to our next order of business.
Okay.
So let's move to our
next order of business.
It's a great way of saying let's move on.
Exactly.
Let's pass to the next topic.
Mm hmm.
Great.
So in this topic, we heard another
really interesting phrase in the dialogue.
Let's listen.
We need to come up with a clear plan.
So we need to come up with a clear plan.
We need to think of think of a clear plan.
Yeah.
We need to come up with.
Okay.
Our third phrase we
heard in the dialogue is this.
Okay.
I'd like you to head up this project.
So this phrase head up.
This is a great phrase.
It means I'd like you to lead
or take care of this project.
Okay.
And the last phrase
for fluency builder, you
can use when you want to give
someone the responsibility of a job.
We heard this.
So I leave this to you.
So I'll leave this to you.
This is you take charge.
Exactly.
I'll leave this to you.
That's a great way of
delegating a responsibility.
So we're going to leave you to
listen to our dialogue last time.
And be sure to pick up all the great
vocabulary that we just talked about.
Well, right.
Let's move to our next order of business.
As many of you are aware
in recent weeks, there
has been a lot of media coverage
surrounding this bird flu issue.
And it's come to my
attention that our company
lacks any sort of bird
flu contingency plan.
Basically, we need to
come up with a clear plan.
We need to outline
specific actions that our
company can take to maintain critical
business functions in case a pandemic strikes.
So what I'd like to do is first point
someone to look after drafting our plan.
Ralph, I'd like you to
head up this project.
Sure.
No problem.
What issues do you want me to consider?
Well, let's see, there are a few
points we need to be thinking about.
First, I'll need you to
analyze our numbers
and figure out what kind of
financial impact and outbreak I have.
You will also need to
think about how we can
avoid any of our
employees getting infected.
Think of ways to reduce
employee customer
contact, perhaps some IT solutions that
will allow our people to work from home.
I guess you'll need me to focus
employee absence as well, right?
And I'll think about the impact
this will have on our clients.
Hey, what about vaccines?
Should we be thinking about
getting vaccines for employees?
Exactly right.
So I'll leave this to you and well,
we'll review the draft plan in two weeks.
OK, so anyone want to
order some KFC for lunch?
OK, great.
So this contingency plan
idea is really interesting, right?
Yeah, it makes sense
for a company to prepare
in case there is an
outbreak of bird flu.
I mean, they need to
maintain their critical
business functions, even if
all the employees are sick.
OK, right.
I guess that's really important and you
have to forecast all these possibilities.
Like people are going
to be away from the
office or even forecast
less sales, et cetera.
That's right.
The interesting thing
is that businesses that
may not actually be
involved in food production
or raising chickens or something like
that are making these contingency plans.
I find that really fascinating.
So it seems there is a lot of fear out
there about the possibility of a pandemic.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, hopefully they'll
come out with the vaccines.
So we don't have to
worry about these things.
That's true.
But until then, we'll have
to create contingency plans.
That's right.
OK, guys, we're out of
time today and I hope
you enjoyed our lesson
and found all these
words and phrases really useful
and you can apply them in real life.
Alright, guys.
Thanks for listening and be
sure to check out our website,
EnglishPod.com, where you can
leave all your questions and comments.
Marco and I are always
around to answer your questions.
So until then, it's bye.
Goodbye.
(upbeat music)